when I was a college student I took a
Course once in the philosophy of science
and one of the textbooks that we read at
that time was entitled The metaphysical
foundations
for modern science and I remember as I
read that book I was awakened for the
first time to a host of assumptions that
I had been making all of my life about
science
and about living
that I never thought of with respect to
what was behind them or underneath them
we have a tendency in our day to make a
sharp distinction between science or
physics and philosophy in engaging in
the Quest for metaphysical knowledge as
if they were these were two completely
separate categories of investigation
that never really meet
but the reality is that in the
scientific world all kinds of
assumptions are being made constantly
that are really philosophical in nature
let me give a simple illustration of
that
when you go to the doctor and you're not
feeling well and you're looking for
diagnosis and treatment of whatever it
is that ails you
one of the concerns that you have and
one of the concerns that your doctor has
is in trying to determine what caused
this malfunction or your illness it's
the same thing that you encounter when
you go and take your car into the
mechanic he wants to find the cause of
the problem so much of what we're
concerned about in the realm of real
science is the whole question of
causality or of cause
and effect
now
the underlying assumptions behind this
question are assumptions that were
challenged with great depth in the 17th
century
Descartes whom we've already introduced
as the leading figure of 17th century
rationalism was very much concerned
about this question he wasn't simply
concerned about epistemology and
self-consciousness that we've already
looked at but he was interested in how
things relate to each other in terms of
causality
Descartes asks questions like this how
is it
that I can think about doing something
and then translate that thought into
action for example if I decide right now
to take this piece of chalk and throw it
to Roger here in the first row and then
Roger decides to throw it back to me and
I catch it without error of course
as we have this little exchange how is
it that I translated the idea
or the thought of an action
into a physical response into a physical
action I decided to throw the chalk he
caught it and he threw it back and I
decided to catch it and that thought
generated an action of response
so that we can see the thoughts
can result in actions and conversely
actions can give rise to thoughts
now we then ask the question
what is an action
and what is a thought
and maybe we don't think about thought
that much
but
we have to at some point ask ourselves
the question what is thought is thought
merely a physiological response with
synapses and and that sort of thing or
our ideas non-physical
we're asking about the relationship
between mind and matter
remember a professor I once had who was
asked to give a definition of the
difference between mind and matter
and somebody asked him
what is
mind
and he said
no matter
and somebody then said well what is
matter
and he said
never mind
and so with that little game we were
left with the conundrum of trying to
distinguish between mind and matter or
between thought and action well that's
the kind of question that occupied the
thinking of Renee Descartes now in order
to address that question he first of all
sought to give definition to matter and
definition to thought or mind
and seeking the simplest level of
distinction between them Descartes came
up with this distinction that that which
is material
is extended or has the property of what
he called extension
and that which is thought or idea
is
non-extension
now we're not accustomed to thinking in
categories like that in the 20th century
but a similar type of Distinction is the
one that we hear people making
frequently between matter and energy
I once had a conversation with a
professor of physics at a leading
University in America and he was
criticizing my task as a theologian for
speaking about God because he said
you know God talk or language about God
is meaningless in the scientific world
you're always talking in abstractions he
said that can't be
materially defined and I said well
certainly you can sympathize with my
dilemma as a theologian because you have
the same difficulty in physics he said
oh no we don't and I said well
do you ever talk about energy and he
said yes I said what is it
and he said well that's easy it's the
ability to do work
I said I'm not asking for a functional
definition I don't know what I'm not
asking you what it does or what it can
do I want to know what it is because you
guys talk about it as if it were
something some had some Essence to it
and he said well energy is MC squared I
said again I'm not interested it's
mathematical equivalency I want you to
give me it's ontology a description of
its being since in your language you
speak of it as something real as
something that really exists
and then he began to feel something of
the weight of the philosophical
assumptions that were undergirding his
common ordinary language
okay for Descartes in trying to
distinguish between matter and thought
or between thought and action he used
the simple categories of extension that
which is material has extension that is
it has some size to it or shape to it
and fills up space and has some kind of
quantitative
weight to it whereas that which is
immaterial such as a thought
or mind is non-extended meaning it
doesn't take up space and it doesn't
have any weight and when people look at
my mind they're convinced of the truth
of that assessment because it doesn't
take up much space and is certainly not
weighty but in any case the question is
if these ideas or these realities of
mind and matter
are real
and they are fundamentally different in
their basic substantive makeup
how can they possibly
interact with each other or how can that
which is extended
produce an effect or cause and effect
that is non-extended
and conversely how can that which is
non-extended or purely mental give rise
to extension or some physical action
he was asking the fundamental question
of how
causal power functions
and his basic theory was called
interactionism
interactionism which simply affirms that
there is interaction between
mind and action or thought and action
in the process of analyzing this
remember that he was a mathematician
and he was trying to locate the point
in our Humanity where the transition
takes place between thought and action
and he was assuming that that he was
assuming that the transition point
is a point
and I'm using the word uh for a reason
is a point that can be defined in
mathematical terms
how many points
that we have
on a line
well theoretically
According to some people a finite line
can have an infinite number of points on
it because a point is merely a
mathematical concept where a point sort
of hovers between
extension and non-extension
a point
takes up space as it were but has no
definite extension or no definite size
to it it's kind of a hybrid between
extension and non-extension so as a
mathematician thinking a mathematical
categories Descartes sought to find the
point of interaction within us
in what he called the pineal gland at
the base of the brain
which is an instant incidentally and
interestingly enough a subject of all
kinds of new modern research about its
function medically biologically but in
any case
what he argued was there is a causal
relationship between mind and matter
between thought and action that takes
place at a definite point
so that a person can think about doing
something the will is then exercised and
as a result of these non-extended
faculties an actual physical response
takes place
so what we're saying here is that there
is a real causal Connection in the world
between things
not only between thought and action but
between thought and other thought and
actions causing equal and opposite
reactions which is part of the the
physics of that period for every
reaction there's an equal and opposite
reaction
now all that assumes
that some kind of power
is transmitted
through
creaturely
entities
it assumes that it is my power
that is generating the tossing of that
coin the caught tossing of that piece of
Chaka should say to Roger and it is his
power that throws it back and my power
that catches it
now as a Christian the question for
Descartes and thinkers of his age is
where does this leave God
is God to be thought of Simply as the
ultimate first cause of everything
in terms of like the 18th century deists
conceived of God as the great watchmaker
in the sky who made the universe like a
machine
and he put together all the integrated
parts of that machine
and then wound up the machine and then
let it operate according to its own
power whereby God then is simply the
Transcendent Observer of everything that
he starts moving but then once the
action Begins the rest all takes place
through the interaction of objects and
people and so on in this world
now you say well what's the big deal
here well let's Jump Ahead to the 20th
century
I would think it would be a more than
safe bet to say that 99 of the people
who are alive in the world and even 99
percent of Christian people in the world
today
think in terms of the universes
operating on a daily basis
on the basis of its own power
the Assumption of our modern worldview
is somewhat mechanical namely that there
is such a thing as the laws of nature
which laws operate
according to inherent
power
that is power within objects forces
within this world that have built in
power
so that if you were going to use this
analogy later on when we get to David
Hume If You observe a pool game in
progress and you see the one player step
and step up to the table with his cue in
his cue stick in hand
and he then aims acoustic at the cue
ball
and he moves his arm
issuing an excuse stroke as it were a
billiard stroke and the tip of the cue
stick then hits the cue ball
and when that happens what immediately
follows is the cue ball begins to move
and roll across the table and hopefully
hits the intended object ball which had
been at rest once the object ball is hit
by the cue ball then a couple of actions
take place the cue ball can carry them
off the object ball or spin back or
follow forward depending on what kind of
spin you impart to it
and you hope that then the action of the
object balls that it rolls across the
table and sinks into the pocket as you
intended
so that the player is using his mind
he has an intention to carry out a
purpose to to carry out and so he
exercises his force on the cue stick
which then imparts Force to the cue ball
which in part in Parts Force to the
object ball which then moves and goes
into the pocket
and our assumption is that there's some
kind of transfer of energy
going on here in this sequence as we
observe it
so the one thing causes another thing
which causes another thing which causes
another thing
and that that power is real and active
again the Theologian asked the question
well does that mean that the Universe
operates without any assistance from God
other than his imparting the initial
motion or the initial power to his
Universe at the time of creation
again that basic assumption that we make
every time we watch a pool game or watch
other series of events that take place
before our eyes
is an assumption that not every
philosopher has accepted in history and
though Descartes accepted it to a degree
some of his disciples challenged it and
challenged it with a vengeance
and so the problem that we're dealing
with here philosophically and it becomes
a major problem when we deal with
questions of theology is the
relationship between what's called
primary causality
and secondary
causality
now what's the difference
primary causality refers to the ultimate
source of power for every action
and
classically and historically
the Christian faith affirms that the
ultimate power in the universe
by which and upon which every other
power
depends not only originally but Moment
by moment is the power of God
remember the Apostle Paul when he
debated with the Athenian philosophers
said that it was in God we live
and move
and have our being and you recall when
we looked at the early stages of
philosophy in the pre-socratic era that
one of the major questions that
philosophers were discussing was the
question of motion
what makes anything move
which is really a question of causality
and so the Christian view has always
been that God is not only the prime
mover in the sense of the first mover
but that no motion can take place in
this world ever no power can be exerted
at any time apart from the power of God
that God does not create a universe that
functions or operates independently from
his moment to moment empowering of it
the Christian idea is there is no
inherent power in nature but that
Nature's power is always the pendant
upon the primary source of power who is
God now people don't think like that in
the 20th century here a secular view of
the world has virtually
captured the thinking of people today
now again
the theologians of history have agreed
that God exercises his power not alone
they wouldn't say that God is throwing
the piece of chalk when that piece of
chalk goes again to Roger or that God is
throwing it back to me but rather I am
really exercising power I do I am a
causal agent but my power and the causal
power that I transfer here
is secondary
so that the idea was that secondary
causality is real
but always dependent on the primary
source of power
who is God
now as Descartes was wrestling with the
question of the relationship between
thought and action between extension and
non-extension
he at the same time is speaking about
what we would call secondary causality
now some of his most famous disciples
malabross for example and go links
another one in France challenged his
theory of interactionism
and replaced it with a a theory that
really had a very short life in the
history of philosophy and they differed
at minor points between themselves but
their basic position was called
occasionalism
occasionalism and this becomes super
important in The Next Century what
occasionalism meant to the Disciples of
Descartes was this
that when I think that I'm causing this
chalk to fly in the air to Roger and he
catches it oh he missed it that time
because I faked him out that it really
all this is what is going on here is
that I'm exercising no power whatsoever
that the movement of my arm and the
release of my fingers from this piece of
chalk is not the cause of the chalks
moving
the only causal power for the
occasionless was the power of God
and it's simply though it seems as
though I am the agent that's making this
chalk fly across the room really it's
God who's making that chalk move across
the room and at the same time he's
moving my arm and the movement of my arm
and the releasing of my fingers from the
chalk is not the cause of the Chalk's
movement only the appearance of a Cause
it's only the occasion
that happens to happen at the same
second that God invisibly and in a
hidden way
metaphysically is actually doing all the
work and all the action
this raises all questions all kinds of
questions about moral responsibility
about Free Will and determinism and the
like but all I want to say to finish up
today
is the occasionalists
exed out the whole concept of secondary
causality
and they did it for theological
considerations to rescue science
from looking at the universe
in a Godless way
so this becomes a very heated point of
dispute for the next 200 years after the
point has been raised